{"tossups": [{"question": "A reference angle of this size in standard position on the unit circle terminates at the point (0,1) [zero after starting at (1,0). Two angles of this size add together to be a (*) straight angle, and any two angles that sum to this size are called complementary. For ten points, name this value that describes one-fourth of a circular rotation or the size of a right angle.", "answer": "90 degrees (accept pi over 2 radians or 100 gradians; prompt on \"90\" or \"pi over 2\" by asking \"in what unit?\")", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>90 degrees</u></b>", "acceptable": ["90 degrees"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept pi over 2 radians or 100 gradians; prompt on \"90\" or \"pi over 2\" by asking \"in what unit?\""}, {"question": "The production of this form of energy is governed by the Shockley-Queisser limit, and can be concentrated with parabolic dishes or generated by the (*) photoelectric effect in photovoltaic \ufffc \ufffc \ufffc \ufffccells aligned in a large panel. For ten points, name this form of renewable energy that is harnessed from the light and heat radiated by the Sun.", "answer": "solar energy (accept reasonable equivalents like solar power; do not accept or prompt on \"renewable energy\")", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>solar energy</u></b>", "acceptable": ["solar energy"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept reasonable equivalents like solar power; do not accept or prompt on \"renewable energy\""}, {"question": "In this country in September 2015, a camerawoman tripped migrants fleeing from a refugee camp in Roszke. In 2015, Viktor Orban, this country's Prime Minister, ordered fences on its borders with Serbia and Croatia to stop (*) Syrian refugees from entering this country. For ten points, name this European country that, as critics ironically note, is seeking guest workers to work in Budapest.", "answer": "Hungary", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hungary</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hungary"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A poem by this man lists body parts like \"upper-arm, armpit, elbow-socket,\" and he describes \"drops of red / Where on the deck my Captain lies\" in a poem for (*) Abraham Lincoln. \"I Sing the Body Electric\" is by this poet, who said \"I celebrate myself and sing myself.\" For ten points, name this American poet whose collection Leaves of Grass includes \"O Captain! My Captain!\" and \"Song of Myself.\"", "answer": "Walt(er) Whitman", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Walt</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Walt"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "er"}, {"question": "This city is home to the Heinz food company headquarters, and tourists often eat sandwiches dressed with coleslaw and fries at this city's (*) Primanti Brothers. Steelworkers traditionally ate pierogis in this city, which sits at the confluence of the Monongahela, Allegheny, and Ohio rivers. For ten points, name this western Pennsylvania city, the state's second largest city after Philadelphia?", "answer": "Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Harold Brown promoted this object to display the danger of technology developed by Westinghouse and Tesla. William Kemmler was the first victim of this apparatus, which is often nicknamed \"Old (*) Sparky\" but is now seldom used, having been replaced by a three-drug sequence. For ten points, name this object whose use in applying death sentences was phased out in the 20th century in favor of lethal injections?", "answer": "electric chair", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>electric chair</u></b>", "acceptable": ["electric chair"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this painting, a blue-clad servant woman steps in front of a grove of trees with gold-edged leaves to hold out a pink cloth to her mistress. Orange blossoms in this painting fall from the cloak of Zephyr as he blows the title (*) goddess toward shore. For ten points, name this painting by Botticelli in which a seashell delivers the Roman goddess of love.", "answer": "The Birth of Venus (accept Nascita di Venere)", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Birth of Venus</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Birth of Venus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Nascita di Venere"}, {"question": "Giovanni Giustiniani died from wounds he received while defending this city. This city used a giant chain connected to the Old Galata Tower to prevent ships from accessing the Golden (*) Horn. Orban designed the giant \"Basilica\" cannon to target this city's Theodosian Walls in a 1453 siege led by Mehmed II. For ten points, name this city, the capital of the Byzantine Empire, which was renamed to Istanbul in 1930.", "answer": "Constantinople (do not accept Istanbul or Byzantium)", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Constantinople</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Constantinople"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "do not accept Istanbul or Byzantium"}, {"question": "In Amonton's Laws, the effect of this force is independent of surface area. This force's magnitude is equal to a namesake coefficient, symbolized mu, times the normal force. One type of this force prevents resting objects from (*) sliding and can be overcome with lubricants. For ten points, name this force that opposes motion between bodies in contact.", "answer": "friction", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>friction</u></b>", "acceptable": ["friction"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Lakoff and Johnson wrote about these literary devices that We Live By, including comparing the state to a father. Examples of this literary device include Dickinson's (*) \"hope is a thing with feathers\" and Shakespeare's \"all the world's a stage.\" For ten points, name this literary device that compares two things without using \"like\" or \"as,\" unlike a simile.", "answer": "metaphor", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>metaphor</u></b>", "acceptable": ["metaphor"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This holiday's seven principles are represented by a kinara holding seven black, red, and green candles that are lit throughout this holiday.This holiday was established in 1966 by Maulana Karenga, who named it for a (*) Swahili phrase meaning \"first fruits.\" For ten points, name this winter holiday celebrating African heritage, which takes place from December 26 to January 1.", "answer": "Kwanzaa", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Kwanzaa</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Kwanzaa"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After learning of Christine Stuart's engagement, this woman accepts the proposal of her classmate at Queen's College, where she studies to be a teacher in (*) Avonlea. This woman becomes close friends with Diana Barry, and marries Gilbert Blythe after she goes to live with Marilla and Matthew Cuthbert on Prince Edward Island. For ten points, name this orphan who lives at Green Gables.", "answer": "Anne Shirley Blythe (accept either underlined name; accept Anne of Green Gables or Anne of Avonlea; prompt on \"Blythe\")", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Anne Shirley Blythe</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Anne Shirley Blythe"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept either underlined name; accept Anne of Green Gables or Anne of Avonlea; prompt on \"Blythe\""}, {"question": "The \"Power Nine\" of this game includes the Moxen and Black Lotus. In January 2017, this game announced the banning of Smuggler's Copter, an Artifact vehicle, from Standard play. A player may lose this game by being (*) \"decked\" or if their life total falls from 20 to 0, due to spells or creature attacks. For ten points, name this trading card game in which planeswalkers tap lands to produce mana.", "answer": "Magic: the Gathering (accept MtG; do not accept Magic the Gathering Online or MtGO)", "category": "Trash", "subcategory": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Magic: the Gathering</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Magic: the Gathering"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept MtG; do not accept Magic the Gathering Online or MtGO"}, {"question": "Workers in this industry were led by Arthur Scargill in a 1984 strike that was defeated by Margaret Thatcher, leading to a decline in this industry, which unofficially ceased in the UK in 2015. The production of this good and (*) steel normalized competition for resources within Europe and inspired the creation of the European Union. For ten points, name this black sedimentary rock that is commonly mined as a fuel source.", "answer": "coal (accept coal mining; accept European Coal and Steel Community; prompt on \"mining;\" prompt on \"ECSC\")", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>coal</u></b>", "acceptable": ["coal"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept coal mining; accept European Coal and Steel Community; prompt on \"mining;\" prompt on \"ECSC\""}, {"question": "This man helped Atlas steal apples from the Hesperides and rerouted two rivers to clean the Augean stables. This man killed Hippolyta and stole her girdle, and at the request of Eurystheus, he used the (*) hydra's own venom to kill it. As a baby, this hero defeated a pair of snakes sent by hera. For ten points, identify this Greek who slew the Nemean lion as one of his twelve labors.", "answer": "Heracles (accept Hercules until \"Greek\" is read)", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Heracles</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Heracles"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Hercules until \"Greek\" is read"}, {"question": "During an experiment named for this material, Hans Geiger counted flashes of light on a zinc sulfide screen, generated after an alpha particle was shot at a foil of this metal; that experiment was overseen by Ernest (*) Rutherford. This highly malleable metal dissolves in aqua regia and is used in electrical connectors to prevent corrosion. For ten points, name this precious metal whose purity is measured on a scale up to 24 karats.", "answer": "gold (accept Rutherford gold foil experiment)", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>gold</u></b>", "acceptable": ["gold"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Rutherford gold foil experiment"}, {"question": "A character in this novel gets a piece of parmesan cheese from Dr Livesey's snuff box in exchange for his help. In this novel, Dick Johnson tears a page from a Bible to make a (*) \"black spot,\" and Billy Bones tells Jim Hawkins to look out for the cook aboard the Hispaniola. For ten points, name this novel about Long John Silver's search for Captain Kidd's treasure, written by Robert Louis Stevenson?", "answer": "Treasure Island, or the Mutiny of the Hispaniola", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Treasure Island, or the Mutiny of the Hispaniola</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Treasure Island, or the Mutiny of the Hispaniola"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One work by this composer includes a \"limping waltz\" and a dynamic marking of 6 p's for the bassoon; that sixth symphony was premiered just a week before this man's death. A popular work by this composer of the Pathetique symphony quotes the French (*) national anthem and includes cannonfire in its depiction of Napoleon's failed invasion. For ten points, name this Russian composer of the 1812 Overture.", "answer": "Peter Ilyich Tchaikovsky", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Peter Ilyich Tchaikovsky</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Peter Ilyich Tchaikovsky"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Prions are examples of these molecules that have been misfolded into the wrong 3-D shape. Actin and myosin are muscle-based examples of these molecules, which are formed from long chains of amino acids. In nutrition, these molecules provide (*) 4 Calories per gram, the same as carbohydrates and less than fats. For ten points, name this type of molecule, provided in foods like nuts, dairy, and meat.", "answer": "proteins (prompt on (poly)peptide) \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc [roos- \ufffc keh] \ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc\ufffc", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>proteins</u></b>", "acceptable": ["proteins"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on (poly"}, {"question": "This man served as U.S. President during the XYZ Affair. As President, this man suppressed criticism and immigration via the Alien and Sedition Acts. This member of the Federalist Party and first official resident of the (*) White House died on July 4, 1826, the same day as his rival, Thomas Jefferson. For ten points, name this second President of the United States and father of another President, John Quincy.", "answer": "John Adams (prompt on \"Adams;\" do not accept \"John Quincy Adams\") \ufffc\ufffc", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Adams</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John Adams"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \"Adams;\" do not accept \"John Quincy Adams\""}], "bonuses": []}